<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Obsidian Vault]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Obsidian Vault</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 02:36:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 02:36:05 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://jawadateeq.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://jawadateeq.com/" target="_blank">Jawad Ateeq</a> {#jawad-ateeq .site-title}]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>::::::::::: {#wrapper}<br>
::::: site-header<br>
:::: container<br>
::: site-title-wrapper<br><br>:::<br>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href="." target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href="/stories" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a><br>
::::<br>
:::::
<br>::::::: {#container}<br>
:::::: container<br>
::: post-header<br><br>:::<br>::: {.post-content .clearfix}<br>
I turn thirty tomorrow. As yet another decade rolls to an end, I find<br>
myself looking back and wondering: what lessons has it taught? For me,<br>
this is a question worthy of pause and reflection. What follows is my<br>
attempt at articulating insights I have at thirty that I didn't have at<br>
twenty.<br><br>1. Learning the Fundamentals<br>
According to The Defining Decade, our twenties hold the potential for<br>
rapid development. This is one of two developmental phases everyone goes<br>
through (the other is during infancy). Now is the time to start learning<br>
about the world, not by twiddling about with hallucinated hypotheses,<br>
but rather by interacting with the world direclty to get some valuable<br>
feedback. Maybe this means taking more risks, as we gradually let go of<br>
inhibitions learned previously. The more feedback we get, the better we<br>
can model how the world works. Gradually, reckless risk-taking becomes<br>
calculated risk-taking.<br>Certain fundamentals deserve our attention early, because the sooner we<br>
tend to them the more intelligently we can use the limited resource of<br>
time. For example:<br>
<br>Learning about the underpinnings of wealth-creation can help us jump<br>
earlier onto the compound interest bandwagon.
<br>Expanding our inter-personal and intra-personal intelligences can<br>
help us create and sustain healthier long-term relationships.
<br>Maintaining our bodies is a habit best developed early. In my<br>
twenties I thought I could justify a decade of indulgence because my<br>
body did not complain at the time-but it doesn't work like that. The<br>
debts pile up and compound too. The last thing anyone wants is to<br>
reach the gates of their thirties only to be greeted by an<br>
insurmountable pile of health debt.
<br>2. Learning by way of experimentation<br>
Once I dove into curiosity-driven inquiry, I inadvertently began to<br>
level-up:<br>
<br>I took improv and standup comedy lessons (I even ended up doing a<br>
comedy set) which made me realize I actually like being around<br>
people.
<br>I set forth into the vast, intimidating world of dating, persevered,<br>
and eventually met my partner of five years.
<br>I attempted a startup making wearable devices to track form during<br>
workouts - and left a year and a half later once I realized I was<br>
missing important industry experience.
<br>I chose to---consciously---bungee jump off a 200ft high cliff over a<br>
spring lagoon, falling for about eight seconds, three of which were<br>
in free fall. Doing so brought me confidence that I can let go when<br>
I need to.
<br>I made it through a ten-day silent meditation course, and walked out<br>
with extraordinary tools to explore my awareness.
<br>Even the range of music I listen to expanded. I'm not phenomenal at any<br>
of these endeavours, but I know enough to not be in unconscious<br>
ignorance.<br>3. Forging alliances with the right therapist<br>
It's possible to make it on our own, but working alongside others has<br>
the advantage that we grow quicker. People who are close to us in some<br>
ways reflect us to ourselves; the way they react to us (and why) carries<br>
information about our behaviour.<br>Now take this information, put it on steroids, and now we have what a<br>
good therapist can do for us. Not only does such an individual<br>
understand better than most people how the human mind works, but thanks<br>
to interactions with dozens of personalities across a large segment of<br>
the population, they also have reams of case studies pertaining to life<br>
choices and how they played out.<br>I've had profound realizations after hearing my therapist rephrase the<br>
language I use to present problems, and juxtapose them with how others<br>
solved it. It takes some trial and error to find the right therapist,<br>
but it's worth the find. I don't go to a therapist because I feel<br>
there's something wrong with my mind; I go so I can learn how it works.<br>4. Reframing the&nbsp;past<br>
The more we observe our actions and the more actions that we observe,<br>
the more we start becoming aware of the causality in our lives. In my<br>
adolescence I had difficulty opening up because I was bullied as a<br>
child; when no one came to help, I attributed this to a lack of self<br>
worth. As a teenager I was overweight, which had social consequences. My<br>
parents were obsessed with my grades-so much so that I feared not being<br>
top of the class.<br>My twenties brought a more mature lens on the basis of which I could<br>
begin to reframe my past. If I hadn't been bullied, I wouldn't have<br>
known what an abuse of power feels like. Being overweight inspired me to<br>
learn the fundamentals of movement, prompting me to invest in a<br>
professional trainer. And my parents' persistence with my grades paved<br>
my way into one of the finest engineering schools in North America.<br>In our twenties we start to identify the sources of our habit patterns.<br>
Gradually, we delineate our voice amidst the din of a million other<br>
voices. We begin to understand that personality can be designed-so we<br>
need not remain stuck in the habit patterns of the past. This is<br>
liberating to discover.<br>5. Cultivating a support&nbsp;network<br>
At twenty, I was determined to get by on my own. I would keep to myself<br>
and rarely open up. Had you met me then, you would've noticed the<br>
heavily furrowed eyebrows and the missing grin. It wasn't until I risked<br>
vulnerability and ventured into the unknown that I was acquainted with<br>
'my tribe'. When the going gets tough, and that weight in my stomach<br>
just won't go, it helps to know I'm not in this alone. A support system<br>
is just that: a system that supports you when you need it - and laying<br>
down its roots begins (at least) in the twenties.<br>6. Focusing on what needs to&nbsp;grow<br>
There's no free lunch. We can't experience the depth of a long,<br>
monogamous relationship while also seeking the thrill and adventure of<br>
the next sexual partner. A desk job brings stability at the cost of<br>
choice in tasks. A startup can empower one to solve a complex problem at<br>
the price of imbalance in other dimensions in one's life.<br>Everything has a cost; I may not have sensed it at the time, but that's<br>
only because the length of time for the cost to manifest itself had not<br>
yet come to pass. If I'm doing better than someone else in my career, it<br>
doesn't necessarily mean I have answers they don't; I may have simply<br>
chosen to focus on a different path. Perhaps others chose to focus on<br>
family, or doing a startup, or taking time off to go on an adventure;<br>
what they are growing might bear fruit in their 30s and 40s. As my<br>
career counsellor once told me: what we focus on grows.<br><br>So there it is. That's what's going through my head as I stand at the<br>
precipice of my twenties. As so many have told me, the past is to learn<br>
from, and my twenties have certainly brought learning.<br>Now onto discovering what the thirties are going to be about.<br>
:::<br>::: share<br>
:::<br>
::::::<br>
:::::::<br>
:::::::::::<br>:::: container<br>
::: site-title-wrapper<br><br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="about:blank#" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top<br>
aria-label="Back to Top"}<br>
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_blank">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_blank">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_blank">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_blank">jbub</a><br>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/twenties.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/twenties.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 02:32:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/untitled.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Untitled.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 02:24:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>