<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Obsidian Vault]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Obsidian Vault</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:16:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:16:10 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[cicadas]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cicada" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cicada" target="_self">Cicadas</a> are insects that hatch
and live underground for the majority of their lives, and emerge only to
mate. They are as innocuous as they are loud. From high up the tree
barks, the males produce the sound by periodically flexing instruments
called tymbals located in the abdomen. Shortly upon finding a mate and
breeding, they die.By the time I noticed there was something different about the sound of
Cicadas, I had already heard their call many times before. It wasn't
until I stumbled into one of their choir earlier this summer, while
idling in a Torontonian park in defiance of Covid, that it dawned on me
their call resembled other noteworthy sounds, like the theme song to
Interstellar, or the chanting of Tibetan monks. It started to fit the
Cicadian Song evoked an out-of-this-world feeling. The story that
follows is inspired by---and therefore dedicated to---that choir of
Cicadas.Like our music, their music developed in stages. Mihād didn't know it at
the time, but an ensemble of Cicadas was behind the thrumming. Wandering
alone along a muddied country trail during recess one overcast morning,
he hadn't planned on hearing their song, especially here of all places,
at the tail end of a silent retreat. "It's the most thrilling thing and
the most terrifying thing," he would later extol in reverent tones to
confused companions. "It's a mating call," confused companions would
mutter in irreverent jest.By the time Mihād stumbled into The Song, the introduction was already
well under way. The Song drew in the listener, eased him in, and the
Singer knew there was no other way. Had the hum not emanated from up
above, from that perforated canopy of sugar maple birch leaves yet to
succumb to autumn, Mihād would've surely mistaken it for the distant
drone of a combine harvesting wheat from adjoining farmlands. Gently the
tune withdrew him from mental minutiae into a foreign frequency.Now the leader of the band of Cicada, satisfied with such attentive
audience, shifted into dynamic pre-chorus, and the gang joined on cue.
Together they amplified what the intro began, and steadily the tone
ascended---rising and rising, all the while gathering intensity. Up, up,
up it went, not in the linear directness of bottom to up, but rather in
a spiralling transition reminiscent of swirling dervishes.What had begun as a soft serenade now erupted into full-blown crescendo.
Each climb in decibel wrought positive havoc on Mihād's senses. By the
time he realized he had embarked a rollercoaster, the ride had already
crossed the summit of no return.So far from the commotion of commerce, the choir couldn't have hoped for
better ambiance. The Cicadian chorus shook Mihād. He felt struck like a
tuning fork. Up until a few moments ago, Mihād's eyes had delivered
unwavering reports of mud-road, birch canopy and cloud cover. Now they
were dancing to the tune of Cicadian vibrato. Each resounding wave that
crashed into him extracted him further from his reverie and flung him
into him. His surroundings closed on him from all directions. Mihād
couldn't have lost his senses even if he wanted to.An overwhelming surge of energy announced that something ominous was
approaching, like the rising dust around Carthage must have announced
the marching Romans. This emphatic Cicadian rhythm falling from the
trees may as well be falling from the heavens. Mihād sought closeness to
the earth, and like a waterfall to the head the song brought him to the
knees.He didn't realize it at the time, but the Cicadas' Song did not flow in
continuous timbre. Instead it weaved in and out of crescendo, ebbing and
flowing to maintain the potency within its chorus, first administered by
this Cicada, then that, each one stepping up round-robin to bathe him
with musical waterfall.Don't fight. The peaks of Cicadian vibration beat every cell of
Mihād's existence into submission, and the punctuating crests offered
momentary respite. He wasn't victim to the unconsciousness of trance, or
the insensibility of stupor. On the contrary, Mihād was too conscious.
Tremendously aware.All thought drowned. The envoloping vacuum made available every flicker
of leaf, every syllable of wind and every particle of dew. Panting, eyes
agape and mouth ajar, is how Mihād received the flood of sensations.
Seconds melted into hours. Here opened into there. Mihād could
no longer tell soaring from sinking.He thought his head might explode. His heart was pounding in his ears.
His lungs were frantic for oxygen. The Cicadian Song---the rocket---was
now achieving lift-off, and, in spite of the wailings of an unwilling
passenger, The pressure forced his insides outwards.Then---just as Mihād was about to disappear into everything, leaving no
distance between subject and object---the pressure resolved! His senses
dissolved and a swooping darkness took him. Out of unknown depths, a
reel began to unwind...All thoughts ever thought, all feelings ever felt, all relationships
flitted by. There were the earliest images of amma and abba, soon
replaced by memories of dearest schoolteachers. Each flitting thread of
friendship, every flame of passion kindled and doused, every like and
dislike... each zoomed by in an instant.The highest tower, of an island prison,
A captive Arabian, parched and beaten.
With head bowed, with hands cuffed,
Awaits fate, a blade awaiting.Early twilight in high English summer,
A garden's brimming, butteflies aflutter.
A Romeo kneels, a Juliet elopes,
A few miles south, a village befuddled.The name is Tara, dark and slender she is,
Shrouded in translucent purple, perched atop a backless couch she is.
Reminiscent of a colorful life, overlooking marble flooring,
Onto a midsummer afternoon, peering through teakwood windows she is.The boy from Sudan, ran away from the gunman,
Away from the village, dusty and overrun.
He knows not plenty, he knows not riches,
Hidden in a cupboard, never mind the roaches.The Nordic king's torso is bare.
His mares must have water and so must his men.
Scampering between rock and grassy patches,
They must wrestle that which lurks in the darkest den.The pious courageous priestess went down a grey compound,
To save the Yazidi girl whom the plunderer did hound.
All the flames' torches and all the stones' sound,
Could not drown out the evil that hitherto was abound.A diligent student, alone in a dull classroom.
Out comes a fairy, and how the room brightens.
She flutters to him, whispers to him,
She enchants him, and how his eyes widen.And then there was no more. There the reel ended. Abstract as they seem,
Mihād understood everything. The waterfall of energy descending up on
him filled him up to the brim. His senses restored and he looked out
once again onto that muddied country trail. The trail was fenced on one
side with birched bark. This time though, he saw with the keenness of a
little child, unsullied by memory.Tears streamed down his cheeks, and those that caught onto the wires of
his unkempt beard glistened in the sun. Mihād was ready to surrender. He
had found what he wasn't looking for. With gratitude, he lowered his
head down on to the earth and gave back excess energy. When he rose, he
no longer heard The Song of the Cicadas.
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/stories/cicadas.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/stories/cicadas.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Stories/cicadas.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:13:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[the_pursuit_of_zelion]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
"... That's incredible! Just the scale of it is staggering." The
emphasis in Harry Hartman's voice reverberated off the acoustic wall
panels lining the auditorium. A cardioid microphone was perched on his
mahogany desk at the center of the stage. It was presently transducing
Hartman's analog wonder into electrical signals, which sped along
serpentine circuits that ran the length of The Medusa. An array of
antennae located in the spaceship's quarterdekc modulated these signals
and broadcasted a frequency to which most of the Solar System had tuned
into.The stage opened up into semi-circular stands rising majestically one
after the other in dim, undulating arcs until they dissolved into
complete darkness. In addition to the five thousand heads in the stands
nodding their agreement with Hartman, the broadcasting unit registered
another hundred fifty million virtual heads. However, the hologram-ready
screen towering behind Hartman---the HoloVisor---could only capture a
fraction of them.At the center of the Holovisor, the prominent projection of an hourglass
stood out amidst the sea of virtual heads. With every passing moment
more sand trickled out from the bulb above into the one below. A modest
pile had already gathered there. A countdown underneath the hourglass
announced precisely what measure of time remained: ninety cevs. A
hundred cevs make one shirev, and a shirev is the time it takes for one
Type-I ship revolution to complete. One shirev is an eighth of the
Earth's rotation.Ninety CevsThe polyester armchair that stood on Hartman's left was reserved for the
show's guests. Tonight's guest, and the center of everyone's attention,
sat still, with both hands clasped in his lap. Warm rays descending from
the main stage light fell upon his delicate form, which seemed so
fragile that light appeared to pass straight through him. His dark eyes
remained unfocussed as they gazed out into a faceless audience.On paper he was Floyd Ryzen, Professor Emeritus of Anthropology at the
University of Encordia, First Author of The Solarian Encyclopedia and
Founder of Zelion; to Solaris though, he was simply "Professor". A
lifetime at lecture hall podiums had trained the professor to convey
detail in his deliveries; tonight, however, had to be different. With
the hourglass draining incessantly, every syllable had to carry weight.Hartman was first to stir. He put aside the letter he was holding and
produced another one from behind his desk. "Professor Ryzen,
five-year-old Marissa from the Venutian Quarter writes, 'Dear Professor,
dada says we wouldn't be live without you so thanks! Can you help me
please what is your rek-mun-dation'" ---Hartman contained a grin as he
attempted to remain true to text--- "'for what I should be when I grow
up?'"For a few moments, the hourglass slipped from Solarian awareness as the
audience cooed at the innocence in the letter. As Ryzen smiled, his
wizened face broke into a hundred lines, and fifty years appeared
deducted from him. "Dear Marissa," he began softly, "you are very
welcome!" Dotage had lent his baritone a hoarse quality, but as Ryzen
addressed the child it took to a gentler timbre. "As for what you should
be when you're all grown up... the answer is already written inside
you." Then the professor resumed his silent gaze. The audience waited
for more, but when none came, a soft applause broke out."The answer is already written inside you---that's a T-shirt right
there!" cheered Hartman. Brown, winged glasses teetered dangerously
close to the edge of his nose. The cheer in his voice conveyed an
indomitable spirit, one that wouldn't be subdued even by the knowledge
that he'd been second choice as host. He understood his bouncy brand
wasn't congruent with iconic moments like these, so when the network
phoned him in, it took him by surprise. The paycheck was nice, but
Hartman would've done it for the privilege alone.Eighty-Five CevsThe host drew another letter. "Mihād Arkum from the Chelum Belt asks,
'Dear Professor, I'm wondering, in your opinion, which event in
Post-Modern history contributed most to shifting us away from the
socioeconomic systems of the late Modern Era?'"Hartman lowered the letter down onto his desk. In the auditorium, slowly
the atmosphere morphed as the question sank in. The lightheartedness
from the letter before gave way to a grim curiosity. These days, talk of
socioeconomic systems and the late Modern Era invariably conjured images
of a darker time in human history. Every day, at dinner tables around
Solaris, well-meaning elders recounted solemn tales of the Resource
Wars.The guest thought for a few moments. This wasn't the first time he'd
been probed on the anthropological socioeconomics of yesteryear---in
fact, he mused, this would likely be the last--- but, as was habit, he
sought the answer anew."Well, uh, let's see Mihād, it's difficult to identify any single event.
The thing about anthropological processes is that, like most intricate
processes, they often require a horde of chained factors to fall into
place before a more transcendent reality can emerge. Our journey from
the late Modern Era down to present day civilization is no different."
Ryzen consulted the confidence monitor relaying the hourglass from the
edge of the stage. "I'm afraid I can speak to you of only a handful of
those factors."Eighty Cevs"By the year twenty-ninety-four, as humanity stood rebuilding in the
aftermath of the Resource Wars, the socioeconomic systems of that
civilization had already received a substantial makeover. Contemporary
power structures had both the context and the wisdom to realize that
latent factors like compassion, and empathy, went largely overlooked as
far as socioeconomic modelling was concerned. Thus began an era of
unprecedented exploration into such arcane topics as the structure of
emotion, and the nature of consciousness.""Some decades later, Anjali Gupta, an Indian social scientist, published
the first high-fidelity model of human consciousness. Her model
unlocked, amongst other things, empirical research into the inner
workings of human reward systems, collaboration under duress, and
optimal states of individual satisfaction. Gupta's model transformed
psychology; instead of reconstructing maps of meaning through the
ambiguity of natural language, the model offered a generalized map that
could be fine-tuned through interaction with the subject. But perhaps
the grandest achievement of Gupta's model was in revealing what reams
and reams of data had hitherto withheld: that consciousness tends to be
asymptotically unstable.""No matter how the model was tweaked, after a finite time interval, the
modelled consciousness would catastrophically self-destruct more than
ninety-nice percent of the time. An explanation for this pre-destined
self-destruction remained at large for many years, and the problem
troubled one researcher in particular. Ralph Gutenberg, who happened to
be studying causal models of motivation at Berkeley, realized he could
use Gupta's model to augment the sparse datasets on motivational
cause-effect patterns by playing out parametrized episodes of the
simulated consciousness. But it would take work; Gupta's model was the
recipe, but what Gutenberg really needed was an automaton that could
rapidly execute the recipe millions of times, with the flexibility to
plug in different ingredients.""When Gutenberg's team finally built an automaton that could simulate
consciousness, he got to experimenting immediately. And what Gutenberg
found startled even himself: the consciousness implicitly creates a
structure, known later as the integrated ledger, to keep track of its
net activity debt. Using a patched version of Gupta's recipe, Gutenberg
showed that the simulation is asymptotically stable so long as its
integrated ledger is balanced.""In his publications, Gutenberg explains that consciousness incurs an
activity loss if it revokes its awareness from experienced conditions.
Revoking awareness reduces the consciousness' capacity to process
real-time signals, which must then fester in a backlog of unprocessed
signals, borrowing bandwidth from future 'processing'. Gutenberg called
this 'buffering' of old signals a 'loss', because with limited
processing capacity the simulation had to rely on a lower-dimensional,
more inefficient form of decision-making, which led to even higher
losses. On the other hand, the simulation incurs an activity reward if
it increases its awareness to experienced conditions. By controlling
awareness, consciousness can maintain a neutral environment conducive to
ongoing evolution---that is, it achieves stability.""Gutenberg's simulation gave us mathematical intuition that to walk
around with an unbalanced ledger is self-destructive. This Integrated
Ledger Principle, as it came to be known, transformed our relationship
with ourselves. It transformed our judicial systems; the instigator
would eventually 'self- punish', and the victim was at peace from the
knowledge of it. The Principle gave us an objective way to assess
balance, an acid test we still use when picking our leaders. For the
first time in a long time, we built a society that optimizes for balance
in integrated ledgers, rather than optimizing for the will of the masses
like earlier societies that lived by the law of large numbers.""But even though Gutenberg's proof of the Integrated Ledger Principle
was revolutionary, it too suffered from a limitation. Gutenberg's
simulations occurred in a closed system---the simulations couldn't
interact with the real world---which limited their applicability to
real-life situations. That changed with Andrey Heidel, the zoologist
studying plasticity of awareness in Indonesian Orangutans."Seventy Cevs"Heidel had invented the world's first myo-psychic electrode---or 'MPE',
as he called them---to better study the relationship between an
Orangutan's motor neuron signals and its field-of-attention. When Heidel
heard of Gutenberg's work, he scrapped what he was doing, much to the
dismay of his sponsors, and got to work on a different research
interest. You see, the MPE held the potential to feed sensory and
actuator signals directly into the simulation, turning Gutenberg's
closed simulation into an open one. If Heidel were to succeed, his
simulation would be truly revolutionary. For example, such a simulation
would unlock the playing out of episodes concerning real-life events by
using the electrode to fine-tune the pre-trained simulated
consciousness.""Heidel did succeed, and his simulation, which we still use today, made
some profound revelations. One of them was that a unit of consciousness
could be made to balance its ledger faster by shaping the
characteristics of the myo-psychic signal fed into it. His work gave us
a deeper understanding of the relationship between psychological and
physiological makeups. Heidel gave us empirical proof that natural law
is embedded within all conscious agents. His group went on to publish
many corollaries to Gutenberg's Principle, one of which even showed that
the mathematics of consciousness without built-in legality doesn't
work.""And so, Mihād, you see, there are many layers to unpack in your
question. Gupta's work laid the foundation for Gutenberg's Principle,
without which Heidel wouldn't have invented an open simulation. Many
such revolutionary milestones have passed us by on the road to
modern-day systems. Their contributions have given us an evolved form of
scalable government, empirical insights into the nature of
consciousness, and, of course, most fundamentally, another dimension in
our decision-making as we navigate the question of how best to live our
lives."Sixty-Four CevsHartman read: "'Professor Ryzen, what inspired you to create the
Solarian Encyclopaedia?'" "Hmm, let's see... well, as you already know,
a sizeable portion of the literature on state-of-the-art energy
harvestation techniques was lost to the Resource Wars. I think it's safe
to say that without feasible methods of energy production, humanity
would've gone extinct many decades ago. Were it not for the support of
millions of inspired human beings, zillions of dollars in funding, and
the prowess of a dedicated scientific research community, the Resource
Wars would've set humanity back by a few centuries.""And yet our energy demands will continue to rise. We've spent far too
much effort scavenging for non-hydrocarbon-based energy methods to risk
losing it all over again. Starting over would be disastrous for our
space-faring civilization. This encyclopaedia"---Ryzen gestured to the
book on Hartman's desk---"is a culmination of the effort of a community
of forward-thinking leaders, created with the express mission to set
humanity sailing back on course, and to keep it there. We've made
invaluable progress over the last century which must be transmitted to
posterity. This encyclopaedia is our affirmation to our successors that
we played our part to foster a forward trend in the expansion of our
collective consciousness."Sixty Cevs"'Professor, why does Zelion pursue the development of Type II
civilization methods? What's the best way to get there?'"Ryzen sat up straighter. "Well, to start with, getting to Type II, what
we call Project Earth Two Point O' at Zelion, is not vain
ambition---it's necessity." His tone carried the air of a man who had
spent his entire life studying human civilizations. "Energy has been a
decisive factor in determining a civilization's productive capacity for
as far back as recorded history. A civilization capable of harvesting
more energy than another will win in an armed conflict every time---the
Resource Wars made that clear as day.""If there is still any doubt that getting to Type II is a necessity,
consider this. First, collective consciousness must balance its
collective ledger, otherwise it is derailed onto a path of self-assured
destruction. Second, Heidel's simulations show that activity loss tends
to rise with predisposition to existential danger. And third, when
energy supplies stall, existential danger surges. So, you see, it
follows that energy supply must move lockstep with demand. If energy
demand rises exponentially, so must its supply. And ever since the onset
of the Information Age, demand has been rising exponentially.""Opinions vary on how we can get there, but one thing remains clear: we
must move quickly. Whatever we do, we mustn't forget the lessons history
recorded on the road to Type I---lessons which beg us to safeguard
against energy starvation as early as possible." Ryzen checked his
confidence monitor. " This is an important point, so I'll hazard a
brisk walk down memory lane."Fifty-Five Cevs"The beginning of the twentieth century saw the ground shake under the
impact of the first World Wars---the birthplace of the hydrocarbon
machine. This machine paved the path to industrialization, globalization
and the resulting economies of scale. The hydrocarbon legacy of the
World Wars laid the foundation for how the world would derive its energy
for another century. But this innovation came at a price; war optimizes
for speed and efficiency, leaving out such trifling factors as planetary
well-being or fair and equal outcomes. By the time the warning bells
tolled, it was too late; the legacy hydrocarbon machine had taken firm
root. This machine ate the future so the world could go round in the
present.""And so began in earnest a desperate attempt to move away from notorious
hydrocarbons. Battery technology had matured significantly, but
somewhere along the battery production line hydrocarbons had to be
burned to create the energy the batteries stored. The Photovoltaic cell,
a remarkable invention capable of creating electricity from sunlight,
cost too much for the wattage it produced. Renewable biofuel like
Ethanol and Biodiesel burned cleaner than hydrocarbons, but troublesome
monoculture farming thwarted efforts to scale up to global proportions.
Hydrogen fuel cell technology, responsible for the bulk of potable water
aboard this very ship, was still expensive then compared with cheap
fossil-based fuel. So, where then could the world pin its hopes?""Oddly enough, nuclear fission---the principle underpinning nuclear
weapons of mass destruction--- found widespread use in the first half of
the twenty-first century. Then again, perhaps this is not so surprising,
seeing as departments of defence around the globe were eager to fund
this area of research. What's curious though, is that nuclear fission
reactors prevailed despite infamous disasters that remain forever etched
in our collective mind. The fission reaction is a potentially 'run away'
chain reaction, leaving a mushroom cloud in its wake and radioactive
sites that remain hazardous for thousands of Earth years. So, despite
its temporary adoption, the fission reactor's days were numbered.""Which brings us to nuclear fusion. Fusion reactions create temperatures
so hot they create a plasma, which then burns the surrounding fuel. The
triple product of plasma ion density, plasma temperature and the
confinement time govern energy output of fusion reactions. The result is
clean energy, chain reactions that don't run away and dissipate in
shorter half-lives, and above all, energy output to match that of the
stars.""Building fusion reactors though, involved advanced physics rarely
practiced elsewhere. The engineering had to be spot on. It's no surprise
that fusion reactors cost billions of dollars, and it would still be a
few decades before the energy output per dollar made sense. At best,
humanity could fund a few scattered reactors, which may actually have
fuelled the case for a resource war. No; it would still take another
order of magnitude in cost reduction before humanity could take refuge
in fusion.""And all this time, as humanity foraged for sustainably scalable energy,
hydrocarbons---an exhaustible resource---kept on depleting. Fear arose.
The exhaustion of the hydrocarbon would halt all the machinery it drove,
and with it, life as people knew it. From transportation and data
centers to more fundamental requirements like feeding populations and
keeping them warm, all systems would fail.""So, by the time the Resource Wars broke out, the consequences of
burning hydrocarbons had already been foreseen decades ago, but no one
knew how to mitigate them. Yes, new research had set in motion a shift
away from hydrocarbon-based economies, but supply couldn't keep up with
demand. Consumption, even amongst ordinary civilians, was so high that
leaders feared mutiny should they interfere with the layman's lofty
lifestyle.""Of course, corporate malfeasance and political ambition delayed
progress too. Large corporations---the imperialists of the Modern Era---
facilitated hydrocarbon-hungry lifestyles to create more stable income
streams; they called it a 'recurring revenue model'. Sponsorship that
could've funded responsible energy sequestration was used instead to
drive consumerism to soaring heights. A vicious cycle set in:
hydrocarbons fueled supply chains, which encouraged consumerism, which
intensified demand and further stoked hydrocarbon-based supply chains.""Gradually, humans exiled temperance. Unbeknownst, minimalism was
banished. Our collective planet-awareness plummeted. In the wake of
globalization and its economies of scale, producers learned to keep
consumers far removed from their deviant means of production. Pavlovian
consumers fell into the routine of turning a blind eye.""It began in under-resourced societies first; loved ones fell to hunger
and thirst, and of cold in the winter months. The sickly that remained
found little treatment. As the Doomsday Clock struck 2 seconds to
midnight, nations with any last remaining morsels of coal or freshwater
river were met with a sobering thought: they were fated to spend the
last of their frantic days fending off the rest of the famished world."Thirty-Nine Cevs"All this time, humanity was still sitting at point eight on the
Kardashev scale. Every technique in the renewable energy handbook was
either exorbitantly expensive, blatantly unfeasible or impertinently
inefficient. It seemed only a miracle could get us to Type I, and yet
that's exactly what was required, not only to save a dying planet, but
to save a civilization imploding under the weight of its own demands.""And a miracle did happen. Hope came, at the eleventh hour, in the
twenty-sixties. Physicists Sue Lee Kwon and Priyanka Ajithkumar, in an
underground war bunker in South Korea, developed an artificially
intelligent model that narrowed down the search space for possible
temperature-resistant molecular sequences. By conducting an ablative
study with the remaining sequences, Kwon and Ajithkumar invented a new
material, Cermathil, alloys of which we still use in the walls of our
spaceships. Single-handedly, Cermathil reduced implementation costs for
fusion reactors and increased the triple product. The rest, as they say,
is history.""A century's worth of innovation followed, leaving us wielding more
energy than a Type I civilization could dream of. Humanity was able to
rescue itself from itself. Out of the ashes of the Resource Wars we
fashioned for ourselves a new, clean home. Today we have spaceships
dedicated to terraforming future habitats. We've invested in
space-faring solar power centers that can transduce unsullied sunlight
into everything from food and clothing to electricity and shelter. We
can fuse atoms in the endless vacuum of space, at a fraction of the cost
and effort. And of course, we've learned to live within our means. The
capacity to find satisfaction in the tiniest of morsels of greenbread is
the true prize of modern life.""But space life is as yet nascent. To scale to interstellar proportions
will take yet more energy. For one, we would certainly need advancements
in power transmission technology. We know how to store energy well, but
we don't know how to transmit it over the long, incalculable distances
spanning our galaxy without leaking most of it. Broadly speaking, we
have two ways to get to Type II: either we harvest energy at the Sun
(where it is strongest and least attenuated) and beam it back to
Solarian consumers, or we learn to generate megawatts on the go. Solving
efficient energy transfer will set the stage for interstellar expansion,
ending humanity's reliance on a singular Sun. But I hope we can see that
getting there, and quickly, is a necessity which we must start acting on
now."Twenty-Two Cevs"'Professor, do you believe in God?'""It doesn't matter what I believe." The abruptness in the professor's
reply took the audience by surprise.Ryzen must have sensed this, for he explained: "Whatever that term 'God'
points to is non- falsifiable. Science investigates what our senses and
the extensions thereof can perceive. Our senses report through
quantifiable signals, but the quantifiable needs a physical medium for
expression. We can't say much about what lies at the end of the term
God, because what we can say is limited to what our consciousness can
receive through the senses. As soon as one mentions the term God, what
follows is a commentary about an experience devoid of physical
substance. So, while the experience of any one unit of consciousness is
invaluable to itself, it's nothing short of fable to another unit.""The concept of 'God' was invented by consciousness that, in a variety
of ways, arrived upon a state of existence so utterly shocking, that it
transformed the very fibre of its existence. Where previously life was a
dull thrum, now it became magical. Every action used to require thought
and consideration; now one rested in the faith that life would converge
to a global optimum. The state of anxiety and fear that previously ruled
consciousness was itself overruled by unconditional love.""This is the state when the ledger from Gutenberg's Principal balances,
a point when consciousness achieves asymptotic stability. And it so
happens that once there, consciousness cannot help but endow others with
asymptotic stability too. But how to share this inwardly originating
experience intrinsic to one unit of consciousness with other units, when
the only available medium is the language of the physical senses? So,
repetitive practices were invented; each stable consciousness invented a
set of practices---rituals---perhaps supplemented with a guidebook. What
they left behind was code for the consciousness which, when executed,
created conditions that incited the consciousness to restore balance in
its integrated ledger.""Do I believe in 'God'? I say it doesn't affect you in the least. In
fact, I propose a different set of questions: What makes life magical
for you? And have you ever had the experience of unspeakable communion
with another unit of consciousness? If not, I suggest you roll the dice
and take a gamble. Try new things till your answer changes to a
resounding 'yes!'. And once you find it, hold on tightly to the thread
that got you there. Do it over and over until you are roiling in the
unconditional union which is characteristic of that state. This is just
one example of code that can bring balance."Ten CevsAs the last remaining specks of sand trickled away, the mood in the
auditorium grew even more sombre. Solarians had known for many years
that the proverbial sun would set on the crucible out of which humanity
emerged, but as that time drew nigh, the reality of the moment became
disconcertingly inescapable. An occasional sob, an odd sniffle, rose
from the stands. Even Hartman's trained voice faltered."Thank you, Professor Ryzen. Is there... is there anything you'd like to
say? As we near the end of our countdown?"Ryzen consulted the confidence monitor one last time. Then, with a long
exhale, he spoke: "Yes, thank you, Harry. I want to say that this may be
the end for our first home, but I'm grateful that it's not the end for
humanity. Out of apes we fashioned a spacefaring nation that has
transcended nuclear war, disease, and now the death of our planet.
Together, we learned to look past the differences in our beliefs and our
appearances, to instead revel in our diversity, and to see through to
what's actually important, what lies at the core---our collective
consciousness.""But this is no time to rest. We may have a new home amongst the stars,
but this home is untethered. So, we must create tethers. It took the
contributions of millions of people throughout the ages to get here, all
to protect the future promise of a stable, collective consciousness. Let
me repeat and say, this is not the time to rest."Three Cevs"To Solarian leaders I hand the reins of Zelion, where you will find
tools to catalyze the onset of a Type II civilization. In the custody of
Solarian civilians, I leave the encyclopaedia, as a reminder of the
endless potency of human perseverance. And for our children, I leave the
image of the pale blue dot. I hope that all consciousness will
stabilize."Ryzen ended with a smile, just as he had begun.Zero CevsAbout two hundred thousand miles away, the asteroid christened Shiva
destroyed the world called Earth, and with that ended the hologrammatic
transmission of Floyd Ryzen, Professor of Anthropology at the University
of Encordia, and Founder of Zelion, whom Solarians knew simply as
"Professor".
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/stories/the_pursuit_of_zelion.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/stories/the_pursuit_of_zelion.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Stories/the_pursuit_of_zelion.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:13:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[vipassana]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
Why should I meditate?I get this question often. My response: one doesn't need to find
meditation, let it find you when you need it.If you don't have a problem, why solve it? Besides, meditation is one of
those things that you only realize the benefit of after significant
up-front investment. It's unusual for someone to invest in something
they don't understand the rewards of.Even once I explain what I got out of meditation, many don't find
meditation appealing. Improve concentration? I don't need that, I have
good focus. I have to stay still in one place for some time? No thanks.
I have to be remain silent? Count me out. I have to pay attention to
"the sensations" that are arising in my body? Get the f*** out.To be fair, it's very difficult to explain the benefits of meditation,
because I don't have the words to describe it. Our language is based on
the five senses, and meditation is trying to transport us beyond these.
You may have heard this referred to as the "inner world".I can only speak for my own experiences. After practicing Vipassana for
some time, I've become more attuned to how I'm feeling. I've become more
aware of when I'm "bull-shitting" myself and others, and when I'm
creating drama in my relationships (and why). It's strange; there are
times when I am arguing and I can see myself from above myself and know
that I'm only trying to avoid the pain of being wrong, or looking
stupid, or having to apologize for a mistake I made. I know this sounds
like basic life skills, but before I practiced Vipassana I would've
reacted without this awareness.I've also become more sensitive to the intentions of others around me. I
find I can be more tactful because I understand how someone else must be
feeling.I've started paying attention to the causality of things... what led to
this particular event? What triggered it? What were the parameters in
question? The flip side of this is: what will this action lead to? Such
understanding of causality is key for learning from mistakes and making
sound decisions.I've also realized that once we express something as an action, we are
sowing a trigger for the action to happen again. This works both ways,
whether the action has pleasant or unpleasnat consequences. Basically,
our actions are not memoryless systems. What we do sows the seed for who
we are likely to do (and therfore who we are likely to be) in the
future.There's another aspect of what I've experienced with Vipassana, but I'm
not sure how to explain it (or what to make of those experience). I have
had experiences where I've "dissolved" into everything else. There's
some loss of the notion of "Jawad". I'm aware of "I", but the "I"
becomes less important than the awarenss of what's being experienced.I call these "spiritual" experiences, because "sprituality" implies
beyond the world of senses, and such experiences beckon me to consider
the world beyond the signals (senses) received by the "I".In truth, I haven't been diligent with practicing Vipassana (a.k.a
Insight Meditation) consistently. And consistency here, as with so many
other aspects of life, is key. While practicing consistently is still a
goal, I find that I'm still able to get into the meditation after being
away from it for some time. It's like muscle memory; the more one has
practiced a physical movement pattern, the more likely they are to be
able to repeat it.I learned Vipassana at a silent meditation retreat. For ten days,
participants are asked to take a vow of silence, and to live a life
similar to Buddhist monks, by taking the following "precepts": 1) no
lying, 2) no killing, 3) no sexual activity, 4) no stealing and 5) no
intoxicants. The no talking part takes care of 1. Precept 2 was pretty
easy---except when the mosquitos came along.The retreat was located an hour north of Toronto, an area called
Innisville. This is a fairly secluded area, far away from Torontonian
hustle and bustle. There's a lot of stillness in this part of nature,
and that stillness tends to instill humans as well. Stillness is good.
The analogy many spiritual masters give is as follows. If one looks into
turbulent water, the depths remain murky. But with stillness one can see
through to the depths. That's why meditation is more than a tool for
concentration. It's a vehicle to help you peer deeply into yourself, see
what you're made of.In this secluded forest were situated a few wooden structures, some one
storey high and others two-storeyed. The two-storeyed sturctures were
where the dwelling rooms were, with two people to a room. The structures
for men and women were separated. I wonder where persons of
non-traditional gender identity reside.The other structures were for the kitched, and another for the
meditation hall. The meditation hall was a large, open space, sheltered
and usually dark, with a slightly raised platform at the front for
"teachers". The rest of the hall was flat and carpeted (IIRC). We would
use yoga mats and cushions on the floor to meditate. Some people used
chairs.Each day we woke up at 4:30 am to the sound of a tolling bell. We would
head out of our rooms, make our way down to clean up, and then head over
to the meditation hall under the as-yet star-lit sky. Here we would
meditate for an hour and a half before another tolling bell would
announce breakfast was served in the kitchen.The food (and everything else) was compeletely free. Participants are
free to make a donation after they leave but it's not necessary. The
food is vegetarian. The authorities insist this is to keep costs low,
but I found this diet to be very energizing compared to may daily meal.
It was very simple food, whole, unprocessed food, and I was surprised by
how easily it passed through my system. Sadly I haven't been able to
stick to that kind of a diet with my family. Something I want to do more
of day-to-day.It was strange at first to eat and not talk to anyone, let alone make
eye contact. I could see everyone else heading in and out of the
kitchen, and lining up after one another. I could see the volunteer
servers preparing and laying out the food arrangements. But everything
happened without a single word uttered. The silence is defeaning at
first but I soon grew accustomed to it. In fact, once the outer world is
silent, the inner world starts to become noticeable. What's noticeable
can be observed, followed, and eventually "engineered" (or
reverse-engineered).After breakfast, we headed back to the meditation hall for an hour and a
half of guided meditation. The rest of the day was comprised of such
hour-and-a-half chunks of group meditation with a few minutes of break
in between. All said, we meditated for 11 hours a day. It's very
difficult not to notice what's going on within oneself after sitting
still and observing oneself for 11 hours, day days straight. I noticed
my own agitation start to spring up after day 4.At 12 we had lunch (of course, announced by the bell that tolls), and at
5pm we had tea. After this, there would be no food until breakfast the
next day. I was concerned at first, but quickly realized that eating
actually makes meditation harder. It's easier to meditate on an empty
stomach. The body just seems to be more readable without the distraction
of food-processing happening within. Again, sadly, I haven't quite been
able to take this back with me into my life. I tend to abuse food and
use it as a reward mechanism. Much left wanting here.At 8pm there's the final group meditation, which involves a lecture
covering the "theory" behind what was practiced that day. First we
practiced, then we understood the widsom behind the practice. I liked
it. Having been to engineering school, I wonder whether I'd have learned
better this way.The lectures were delievered by S. N. Goenka and are avaiable on<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cz7QHNvNFfA&amp;list=PLPJVlVRVmhc4Z01fD57jbzycm9I6W054x" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cz7QHNvNFfA&amp;list=PLPJVlVRVmhc4Z01fD57jbzycm9I6W054x" target="_self">youtube</a>.
I had the option of viewing these before I went to the retreat, but
decided not to. I'm glad with the decision. I think I would've judged
the quality of the video, or misunderstood some of the ideas therein
without having experienced it myself. Needless to say, these lectures
blew my mind. Regardless of whether the ideas were fact or fiction, the
ideas themselves were fascinating.The meditation itself was divided into two phases. The first phase of
the meditation was a breathing-based exercise called "Ana Pana", which
refers to the breath going in and out of the nostrils. This meditation
was about bringing our attention to the triangle formed from the top of
the nose at its apex, and the upper lip at the base. As the breath
travels in and out, it touches the upper lip. We were asked to pay
attention to the nature of the breath when it enters and leaves. It's
temperature, it's feel, it's volume, it's frequency. The idea here was
to prepare us for body-scanning (the second phase). Since this
triangular area is small, it helps prepare us for eventually
body-scanning the entire body by taking baby steps.The second phase is Vipassana meditation. What we did with the upper
lip, we would not do with the entire body. Starting with the crown of
the head, we would take each "patch" of our skin and rest our attention
there for a few seconds, noticing what sensations are present.
Itchiness, numbness, large unnoticeable patches, small very noticeable
patches, tickles, hot, cold... whatever was going on, the goal was to
just observe, without judging the sensation.The underlying wisdom in this practice is that all our actions stem from
sensations. There's a closed feedback loop between our environment and
us, and if we don't pay attention to this loop that we, being creatures
of habit, will habitually react to our environment. Thus our environment
will contorl us. To break this loop, we prevent the cycle from
completing. The loops looks as follows.First a trigger occurs in the environment. Our senses pick this up and
send out, hint hint, a sense-ation. Our perceptive centers judge the
sensation as pleasant or unpleasant, based on a few factors, including
past experiences. How we react to a sensation will be recorded in this
perceptive center, which is why our actions are so important. This is
how trauma is stored in the body. Positive learning is also stored in
the body (that's a fire, I mustn't touch it!). The goal is not to
indiscriminately forget all the past. The goal is to not react to the
sensations that are coming up, but to be able to look at them anew and
make the right decisions in the present.The point at which we can break the feedback loop is when the sensation
is first noticed. If we don't notice it, the perceptive center will
automatically judge it and create a reaction. But if we can sense the
sensation, remain equanamous (neither develop an attachment or an
aversion to it), we start to weaken the judgement, or labelling, around
that sensation. The next time that sensation comes up, we're more likely
to be robust to it, and instead of reacting unconsciously, repsond to it
consciously.This was so long ago, but I still remember being there vividly. I'll try
do another one of these retreats soon, they really do transform you.
They're not the easiest thing to do, especially when you come out of a
secluded, quiet forest and into a bustling city like Toront which is
pregnant with sound. It can be a lot. But these excursions made me
realize that there's so much unconsciousness in my life and if I am to
grow beyond my current condition, I must weaken the hold that my
environment has on me.
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/vipassana.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/vipassana.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/vipassana.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:12:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[physical_fitness_journey]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: {#container}
:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: container
::: post-header:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
March 01, 2024::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240201/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240201/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240201/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::♪ Just keep swimming, just keep swimming. ♪January 22, 2024::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240131/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240131/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240131/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::Dear Diary,I have gained 3 KGs. Wow.Not sure what to make of it. My gut reaction was to spiral into a
viscious cycle of self-defeat. Then I remembered that my clothes
actually fit better, and I'm moving better than a year ago. Think
long-term.My self-defeatist attitude was debilitated by the fact that my right
shoulder's been hurting for the past month. Today, sure enough, it
started acting up again. A terrifying image flashed before my eyes, one
in which I was living with a chronically damaged shoulder.I must keep going. The alternative is to sit at home and do nothing, and
that's what got me into the mess I'm in. Fatigue, trouble standing up
straight, overweight and immobile. One step at a time.On the bright side, I learned a few things too. First, the right
shoulder hurts because it collapses forward, which happens because the
left side of the lower back isn't firing (due to a past injury). Fix the
lower back, get the right lat muscle firing, and the shoulder pain will
resolve.Second, I've been noticing that my elocution---which has suffered
tremendously since Covid, in the sense that I mumble and sound
monotonous and languished---improves tremendously when I stand up with
symmetry. Standing up with symmetry just means that I'm loading both
feet equally. This isn't the case today, because of the aforementioned,
inactive lower back on one side. My torso tends to twist to the left.
Because of this I don't stand up straight, which leads to a neck that
rolls forward, throttled breathing and muffled speech. Fix the back!!Seems like today is a day of realizations. I solved another problem
ailing me for years. The Android Auto in my car just wouldn't accept my
phone. It would accept every other phone we tried, just not mine. I even
switched phones, and still it refused to connect. I changed cables. I
deleted my phone from the car and reconnected. I played around with
Google's privacy settings on my phone. No change. For two years I've
been magnetically mounting my phone on the vents and using it directly
(what a tragedy, I know). I was venting to my partner today, and just
decided to factory reset the car system. After 10 minutes of waiting for
a factory reset---BOOM, the phone connected!Thank you, Universe.January 15, 2024Dear Diary,Today someone at the gym asked me what my biggest takeaways were after a
year of calisthenics. I was taken aback by the question, because I
didn't expect someone to ask me this seeing as I'm still visibly out of
shape. Having said that, the answer I gave him formed gradually, bit by
bit, after various iterations.Here's what I said about my three biggest takeaways.Consistency and persistence take precedence above all else. The body has
considerable momentum in a non-conducive direction coming in. It needs
small, repeating stimuli to change momentum in a more positive
direction. Show up even when you don't feel like it. Over time, you want
to be anywhere else.Second, patience is an important virtue. Rome wasn't built in a day.
Having a long-term perspective is important, otherwise you'll get
demotivated. At first, I wanted to say I'm going to do this for a few
months. Then a year. Eventually I realized it's more important to
develop a habit than getting to a set of "six pack abs". Besides, even
if I somehow get to a set of six pack abs, and don't have a long-term
perspective, my old habits would take over anyways.Third, it'll be tough to show up consistently if you're not having fun,
so invest in a sense of community. Build a network. Exchange
pleasantries. Trade comments and strategies. The community will keep you
coming back, tying into point number two above, of having a long-term
perspective.January 10, 2024Dear Diary,I'm going through one of those "ebbing" phases, the ones where I find
myself waning into relaxation instead of driving forward. I am allowing
myself this waxing and waning, temporarily, so that I may return to the
"flowing" phase with vigour.I must keep careful watch though. One day turns into two, two into
three, and before I know it, months go by being away from physical
activity.I've been doing the rotational hip mobility exercises the chiropractor
gave me. It's been a week. In the gym I felt slightly more stability on
the plank, resulting in me holding the plank for longer this week. So
I'm optimistic this exercise will restore some of the imbalance I've
been suffering in my hips for the past few years.The hamstring on the left side, which had been so tight and painful the
last week, is slowly being releaved. It's still tight, but I feel good
things are on their way.Even though the wall handstands this week were difficult, with me hardly
being able to move closer to the wall, and my right shoulder hurting
afterwards, I feel there is more stability coming this way. On the
handstands I remained aware of keeping both hips balanced, and that
resulted in the right shoulder pulling more of its weight. Will have to
keep doing this.I'll return to the gym soon.December 2023Dear Diary,I dropped the ball back in October, and have been making my way back
slowly and steadily since. It's funny how quickly time passes when
you're not in the gym, lounging on the couch, eating crap and being
hedonistic in general. It's funnier (not really) how much time slows
down when you're doing the heavy work of getting your ass to the gym
every day.Every day, the struggle starts anew. I decided a while ago that I will
go into the gym everyday, with a day or two of rest as needed. It hasn't
been easy, every inch of my body hurts. But I decided to do this because
leaving gaps in between means even more pain when I get back into the
gym. It took me a year to figure this out.::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20231222/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20231222/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20231222/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::I've noticed some positive changes in the last two months. In the gym
everyone knows me as 1) the bigger guy (I'm assuming, no one's implied
this), and 2) the flexible guy. My flexibility has improved in many
ways.The other day someone fist-bumped me because he noticed how much weight
I've lost. A close friend commented I've dropped a lot of pounds. So
it's showing.Strangely, the weighing machine still shows 111KGs. I suppose I've been
putting some muscle on, and the clothes are fitting better. Still feels
annoying that the gut is big, but these things take time. So gotta keep
patient.I ended up seeing a chiropractor for the mobility issues in my left hip.
It's been two months and I haven't seen improvement from exercise alone.
The chiro told me my hips are very tight (which is strange, because I
have pretty good flexibility bending forwards), but rotational mobility
is quite weak. He gave me some stretches and exercises to do three times
a day. Let's see what happens.September 2023Dear Diary,It's already been a year. I renewed my membership to the calisthenics
gym for another year.I haven't been consistent throughout the year. Rather, there are bursts
where I'm consistent for a few three-month legs in the year. The rest of
the months my motivation was dwindling, I was doubting myself, or I was
being plain lazy.It's alright though, over the long run it's better to develop good
habits, which I'm doing.If the pain gets too much, I won't want to be consistent anyways.August 2023Dear Diary,I have a nice ritual going. I listen to podcasts on the way to and from
the gym. The drive there and back are "me" times. I listen to the Lex
Fridman podcasts, or depending on my mood, Joe Rogan.::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230813/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230813/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230813/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::I'm noticing I'm starting to move better. I can hang for 60s now. Dips
are still hard, something feels off in my right shoulder. The Australian
push-ups are pretty tough still, can't get past 30 seconds. Planks are
pretty hard too but I know I'm progressing.May 2023Just keep going. Just keep going.::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230503/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230503/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230503/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::April 2023::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230423/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230423/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230423/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::March 2023::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230313/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230313/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230313/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::Jan 2023Dear Diary,Got back into it in the new year. I had given up in the past couple
months. I feel like such an odd person out at the gym. Even though
everyone's great, I know what everyone must be thinking.::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230119/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230119/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20230119/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::Still, I've gotta remember what brought me to Calisthenics, and stay
committed. Small efforts, repeated, will complete any undertaking. One
step at a time is not too difficult.October 2022::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20221029/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20221029/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20221029/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::Septermber 2022::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220909/front.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220909/side.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220909/back.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::August 2022<br>The owner and instructor at <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://uc-results.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://uc-results.com/" target="_self">Ultimate
Calisthenics</a>, Alex, asked me to take pictures
of myself regularly to track progress. I feel very vulnerable putting
these here... what if my boss sees it? What if my extended family sees
it?Let them see. I'm a lion, right? Lions take risks.Here's the first set of them.::: img_row<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220810/20220810_195345.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220810/20220810_195353.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}<br>
<img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20220810/20220810_195404.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">{.img_dimensions}
:::After coming back from the Calisthenics gym, I feel very dejected. I saw
people with rock hard abs doing jumping lunges, iron crosses, ring
muscle-ups... and here I'm struggling to warm-up properly.It's going to be a very long road.<br>Here are a few other excerpts from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.amazon.ca/Greatest-Salesman-World-Og-Mandino/dp/055327757X" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.amazon.ca/Greatest-Salesman-World-Og-Mandino/dp/055327757X" target="_self"><em></em></a>The Greatest Salesman In The
World
that're keeping me going.
"The prizes of life are at the end of each journey, not near the
beginning, and it is not given to me to know how many steps are
necessary in order to reach my goal. Failure I may still encounter at
the thousandth step, yet success hides behind the next bend in the
road. Never will I know how close it lies until I turn the corner.
Always will I take another step. If that is to no avail, I will take
another, and another. In truth, one step at a time is not too
difficult."
---Scroll III, The Greatest Salesman In The World "I will build my castle one brick at a time, for I know that small
efforts, repeated, will complete any undertaking."
---Scroll III, The Greatest Salesman In The World
Love,
JawadPS: My partner says the hair on my belly looks like a christmas tree.
She's not wrong...(Still Later) July 2022Diary Diary,<br>I've joined a Calisthenics gym. It's called <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://uc-results.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://uc-results.com/" target="_self">Ultimate
Calisthenics</a> and is located in Toronto. Wish
me best.Love,
Jawad(Later) July 2022Dear Diary,Here are some videos of things I want to be able to do.::::::: {style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;"}
:::::: iframe
::: {#player}
::::::: player-unavailable::: submessage<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0sd-M1rB_oI" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0sd-M1rB_oI" target="_self">Try watching this video on
www.youtube.com</a>{target="_blank"},
or enable JavaScript if it is disabled in your browser.
:::
::::
::::::
:::::::::::::: {style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;"}
:::::: iframe
::: {#player}
::::::: player-unavailable::: submessage<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhl2TRnSiNM" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhl2TRnSiNM" target="_self">Try watching this video on
www.youtube.com</a>{target="_blank"},
or enable JavaScript if it is disabled in your browser.
:::
::::
::::::
:::::::::::::: {style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;"}
:::::: iframe
::: {#player}
::::::: player-unavailable::: submessage<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YMthB9Lamy4" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YMthB9Lamy4" target="_self">Try watching this video on
www.youtube.com</a>{target="_blank"},
or enable JavaScript if it is disabled in your browser.
:::
::::
::::::
:::::::I'll look for some Calisthenics gyms near me.Love,
JawadJuly 2022Dear Diary,Something needs to change.My body feels like a prison. It lacks the most basic range of motion
required to accomplish the simplest tasks. I get drained so easily. From
meditating and body scanning, I notice unpleasant sensations arising
more often than when I was in better shape.It goes without saying I don't like how the person looking back at me
from the mirror looks. This affects my confidence. My confidence affects
my performance at work and in my relationships. I'm not applying myself
fully.A throttled body doesn't express itself well. When one doesn't express
oneself with high fidelity, other people don't lean in. So constipated
expressiveness is reducing my ability to persuade others. This is
shortening my raidus of impact.At a mental level, I lack the persistence, drive and endurance to last
long enough to accomplish anything of substance. I'm living life in the
short-term. I'm letting the winds of life move me as they please.Something needs to change.The following excerpt from a book that Matthew McConaughey recommended
resonated with me.
"I was not delivered unto this world in defeat, nor does failure
coarse through my veins. I am not a sheep waiting to be prodded by my
shepherd. I am a lion, and I refuse to talk, to walk, to sleep with
the sheep. I will hear not those who weep and complain, for their
disease is contagious. Let them join the sheep. The slaughterhouse of
failure is not my destiney."
--- Scroll III, The Greatest Salesman In The World.
Enough weeping and complaining. Time for some action.Love,
Jawad
:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: share
:::
::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::
:::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::
::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/physical_fitness_journey.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/physical_fitness_journey.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/physical_fitness_journey.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:11:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240201/front.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://jawadateeq-images.s3.ca-central-1.amazonaws.com/physical_fitness_journey/20240201/front.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[success]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
Success is in remaining unattached---from money, sex and a high bed.
Success is in building a mansion, with the will to walk away and
inhabit a shed.Success is in so outwitting the beast, that to fight is unnecessary.
Success is in so disciplining the Self, that no addiction is
adversary.Success is in greeting the day with love, and ending the night with
praise.
Success is in charging forward again in spite of the sting of the
blade.Success is in amassing the wealth of ability, not hoarding the fruits
thereof.
Ultimately, success is in knowing intimately the Universe and the
entrails thereof.
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/success.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/success.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/success.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:11:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[year_in_review]]></title><description><![CDATA[::::::::::: {#wrapper}
::::: site-header
:::: container
::: site-title-wrapper:::
<a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
Another year gone.It seemed that this year I emerged from a long, dark passage of the
soul. I had been "imprisoned" in this passage for a few years, at least
since I turned thirty three years ago. Of course, hindsight is 2020. I
needed that dark passage to understand better what path to take.Whilst in this dark passage, I felt incapable of bearing the ongoings in
various dimensions of my life. Pandemic notwithstanding, the stressed
stemmed from dimensions including dysfunctions within the family,
career's constant upward and onward pressure, and a nagging feeling that
I'm not living up to my truest potential.I didn't have good coping mechanisms either. I took the pressure from
the various dimensions of this life, and beat myself up constantly. I
resorted to suboptimal coping mechanisms, leading to reduced impulse
control.Most of this year I remained shrouded in darkness. I am surprised at how
I functioned, really. There was a constant stream of thought occupying
the limited capacity of my brain, leaving no room for problem-solving.Over the course of a few years this led to deteriorating health (I put
on 60lbs) and . I lost sight of who I really was. I started to lose
confidence that I could move moles, let alone mountains. I felt
impotent, unable able to effect anything or anyone.But later this year, something clicked and I decided I had had enough. I
realized that there were things I could take charge of, and others that
I couldn't really control. This is a lesson emphasized in<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://jawadateeq.com/posts/vipassana/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://jawadateeq.com/posts/vipassana/" target="_self">Vipassana</a>: don't get attached
to the contents of life, and don't run away from them either. Life is
constant flux; try to remain equanimous. Bruce Lee called this "be like
water".It was time to get to work. Rather than being reactive, it was time to
take control of how I was spending my time, and to do everything I could
that was within my circle of control. I decided to move forward in my<br>
relationship, starting by propopsing to my now fiancee. I joined <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://jawadateeq.com/posts/physical_fitness_journey/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://jawadateeq.com/posts/physical_fitness_journey/" target="_self">a
Calisthenics
gym</a> and started
my journey towards moving the way I've always dreamt of. I started
working on more "spiritual" matters, beginning with practices that
remind me daily why I'm here, and to center me when the ups and downs of
life threaten to derail me. I also made some progress on where I want to
head towards in my career.Next year, I will take my focus on health to the next level, by also
focusing on how I eat. At the moment food has become one way to reward
myself, and I must learn how to balance this with "food as fuel". I plan
to advance with calisthenics as well, by acheiving my goal of doing my
first pull-up as well as my first muscle-up. I have other goals too, so
I'm optimistic for 2024.Yes, there's a lot of pain out there in other parts of the world. And
the best thing I can do for the world is to not be a part of the
problem. I must become powerful and potent, so that when the time comes,
I can apply myself and bring the world towards better outcomes.
Idealistic, yes. Better this than wallowing in my self-pity.
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/year_in_review.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/year_in_review.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/year_in_review.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 03:10:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[twenties]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a href=".?query=tag:blog/post" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#blog/post">#blog/post</a>:::
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Posts</a>
<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="/stories/" href=".html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stories</a>
::::
:::::
::::::: {#container}
:::::: container
::: post-header:::::: {.post-content .clearfix}
I turn thirty tomorrow. As yet another decade rolls to an end, I find
myself looking back and wondering: what lessons has it taught? For me,
this is a question worthy of pause and reflection. What follows is my
attempt at articulating insights I have at thirty that I didn't have at
twenty.1. Learning the Fundamentals
According to The Defining Decade, our twenties hold the potential for
rapid development. This is one of two developmental phases everyone goes
through (the other is during infancy). Now is the time to start learning
about the world, not by twiddling about with hallucinated hypotheses,
but rather by interacting with the world direclty to get some valuable
feedback. Maybe this means taking more risks, as we gradually let go of
inhibitions learned previously. The more feedback we get, the better we
can model how the world works. Gradually, reckless risk-taking becomes
calculated risk-taking.Certain fundamentals deserve our attention early, because the sooner we
tend to them the more intelligently we can use the limited resource of
time. For example:
Learning about the underpinnings of wealth-creation can help us jump
earlier onto the compound interest bandwagon.
Expanding our inter-personal and intra-personal intelligences can
help us create and sustain healthier long-term relationships.
Maintaining our bodies is a habit best developed early. In my
twenties I thought I could justify a decade of indulgence because my
body did not complain at the time-but it doesn't work like that. The
debts pile up and compound too. The last thing anyone wants is to
reach the gates of their thirties only to be greeted by an
insurmountable pile of health debt.
2. Learning by way of experimentation
Once I dove into curiosity-driven inquiry, I inadvertently began to
level-up:
I took improv and standup comedy lessons (I even ended up doing a
comedy set) which made me realize I actually like being around
people.
I set forth into the vast, intimidating world of dating, persevered,
and eventually met my partner of five years.
I attempted a startup making wearable devices to track form during
workouts - and left a year and a half later once I realized I was
missing important industry experience.
I chose to---consciously---bungee jump off a 200ft high cliff over a
spring lagoon, falling for about eight seconds, three of which were
in free fall. Doing so brought me confidence that I can let go when
I need to.
I made it through a ten-day silent meditation course, and walked out
with extraordinary tools to explore my awareness.
Even the range of music I listen to expanded. I'm not phenomenal at any
of these endeavours, but I know enough to not be in unconscious
ignorance.3. Forging alliances with the right therapist
It's possible to make it on our own, but working alongside others has
the advantage that we grow quicker. People who are close to us in some
ways reflect us to ourselves; the way they react to us (and why) carries
information about our behaviour.Now take this information, put it on steroids, and now we have what a
good therapist can do for us. Not only does such an individual
understand better than most people how the human mind works, but thanks
to interactions with dozens of personalities across a large segment of
the population, they also have reams of case studies pertaining to life
choices and how they played out.I've had profound realizations after hearing my therapist rephrase the
language I use to present problems, and juxtapose them with how others
solved it. It takes some trial and error to find the right therapist,
but it's worth the find. I don't go to a therapist because I feel
there's something wrong with my mind; I go so I can learn how it works.4. Reframing the&nbsp;past
The more we observe our actions and the more actions that we observe,
the more we start becoming aware of the causality in our lives. In my
adolescence I had difficulty opening up because I was bullied as a
child; when no one came to help, I attributed this to a lack of self
worth. As a teenager I was overweight, which had social consequences. My
parents were obsessed with my grades-so much so that I feared not being
top of the class.My twenties brought a more mature lens on the basis of which I could
begin to reframe my past. If I hadn't been bullied, I wouldn't have
known what an abuse of power feels like. Being overweight inspired me to
learn the fundamentals of movement, prompting me to invest in a
professional trainer. And my parents' persistence with my grades paved
my way into one of the finest engineering schools in North America.In our twenties we start to identify the sources of our habit patterns.
Gradually, we delineate our voice amidst the din of a million other
voices. We begin to understand that personality can be designed-so we
need not remain stuck in the habit patterns of the past. This is
liberating to discover.5. Cultivating a support&nbsp;network
At twenty, I was determined to get by on my own. I would keep to myself
and rarely open up. Had you met me then, you would've noticed the
heavily furrowed eyebrows and the missing grin. It wasn't until I risked
vulnerability and ventured into the unknown that I was acquainted with
'my tribe'. When the going gets tough, and that weight in my stomach
just won't go, it helps to know I'm not in this alone. A support system
is just that: a system that supports you when you need it - and laying
down its roots begins (at least) in the twenties.6. Focusing on what needs to&nbsp;grow
There's no free lunch. We can't experience the depth of a long,
monogamous relationship while also seeking the thrill and adventure of
the next sexual partner. A desk job brings stability at the cost of
choice in tasks. A startup can empower one to solve a complex problem at
the price of imbalance in other dimensions in one's life.Everything has a cost; I may not have sensed it at the time, but that's
only because the length of time for the cost to manifest itself had not
yet come to pass. If I'm doing better than someone else in my career, it
doesn't necessarily mean I have answers they don't; I may have simply
chosen to focus on a different path. Perhaps others chose to focus on
family, or doing a startup, or taking time off to go on an adventure;
what they are growing might bear fruit in their 30s and 40s. As my
career counsellor once told me: what we focus on grows.So there it is. That's what's going through my head as I stand at the
precipice of my twenties. As so many have told me, the past is to learn
from, and my twenties have certainly brought learning.Now onto discovering what the thirties are going to be about.
:::::: share
:::
::::::
:::::::
::::::::::::::: container
::: site-title-wrapper<br><a class="internal-link" data-href="#" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/twenties.html#_0" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"></a>{.button-square .button-jump-top .js-jump-top
aria-label="Back to Top"}
:::<br>© 2024 / Powered by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://gohugo.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_self">Hugo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/roryg/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ghostwriter theme</a> By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://jollygoodthemes.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://jollygoodthemes.com" target="_self">JollyGoodThemes</a> /<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub/ghostwriter" target="_self">Ported</a> to Hugo By<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/jbub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/jbub" target="_self">jbub</a>
::::]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/twenties.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/twenties.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[hello world<a data-href="twenties" href="jawadateeq.com/blog/twenties.html#_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">twenties</a> February 20, 2025]]></description><link>jawadateeq.com/blog/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">jawadateeq.com/Blog/index.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 02:55:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>